<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ho kalos agon tes pisteos. The good fight of faith. Being the substance of a sermon preached to the congregation assembled at the interring of the body of Master William Hill lately one of the magistrates of Guildford in Surrey. / By his sonne in law Francis Peck, Master of Arts, sometimes preacher there, and now minister of God's word in Hertford.</title>
            <author>Peck, Francis, d. 1651.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90348</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1031</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E286_25</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200082</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860886</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860886</idno>
            <idno type="VID">158543</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90348)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 158543)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 47:E286[25])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ho kalos agon tes pisteos. The good fight of faith. Being the substance of a sermon preached to the congregation assembled at the interring of the body of Master William Hill lately one of the magistrates of Guildford in Surrey. / By his sonne in law Francis Peck, Master of Arts, sometimes preacher there, and now minister of God's word in Hertford.</title>
                  <author>Peck, Francis, d. 1651.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Enderby, and are to be sold at his shop at the Starre in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first five words of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 5th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Timothy, 1st VI, 12 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:158543:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>THE GOOD FIGHT OF FAITH. BEING The Subſtance of a Sermon Preached to the Congregation aſſembled at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terring of the body of Maſter <hi>William Hill</hi> lately one of the Magiſtrates of <hi>Guildford</hi> in <hi>Surrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By his Sonne in law Francis Peck, Maſter of Arts, ſometimes Preacher there, and now Miniſter of God's Word in <hi>Hereford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Enderby,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the Starre in <hi>Popeſ-head Alley,</hi> 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:158543:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:158543:2"/>
            <head>To the vertuous Widow, and hopefull Off-ſpring of that eminent Servant of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, Mr. William Hill, one of the Magiſtrates of the ancient Burrough of <hi>Guildſord</hi> in <hi>Surrey.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Precious and Beloved:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here be but two irreſistable arguments <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> any ingenuous nature to reſigne ones ſelfe to the deſire of another, <hi>viz.</hi> That of duty, and that of affection; both which (you know) hath ſtrongly engaged me both to preach and print this Sermon, upon this ſad and ſodaine occaſion; the former task required by the deceaſed himſelfe, whoſe very relation (being a Father ſo full of care and affection to us all) heares the nature of an injunction, not to be diſobeyed: the latter importuned by the concurrent requeſt of you all ſurviving ſo neerly related; that except I could put off duty and humanity at once, without all dispute, you muſt be alſo gratified: which undertaken, I preſume to make mine earneſt requeſt to you all in ſome few particulars; which I hope the Lord Jeſus will both move and enable you readily to condeſcend to me in, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb facs="tcp:158543:3"/> 1. That ſo precious a patterne and preſident of vertue and piety be really imitated of you all.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That you be practicall, and turne the words you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired of me, into the works which God requireth of you.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That by the ſavory <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction of brotherly concord amongſt our ſelves, you will endeavour with me to be ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolatory to our deare ſurviving Parent, that albeit we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſupply her invaluable loſſe, yet we may argue our gratefull acknowledgment of her right commendable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour to, and paines with him who is now with the Lord.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly, that you will excuſe me, and make mine apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy for ſpeaking ſo little in the prayſe of him that deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſo much; mine affection and experience indeed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigates: but counſell to one ſo aproximate muſt be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>viz. Let another praiſe thee and not thine owne</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 27. 2.</note> 
               <hi>mouth; a ſtranger, and not thine own lips.</hi> So I commend you to the provident care of him who is faithfull, and bath promiſed ſo much to the widow and fatherleſſe; and in him, according to my ſeverall relations, to each of you, reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, F. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:158543:3"/>
            <head>THE GOOD FIGHT OF Faith.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 TIM. 6. 12.</bibl>
               <q>Fight the good Fight of Faith: Lay hold on Eternall Life.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N theſe fighting times, whereunto by the provident hand and juſt vengeance of God, we are fallen: In which ſad warres, many poore ignorant ſoules, and many prophane, atheiſtical blaſphemous, idolatrons wretches are ingaged, utterly unfit to live, and as ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly unprepared to dye; when ſuch on both ſides hath fought this fight, and death ſeizeth on them, they lay hold on eternall death, and everlaſting torments, in the burning lake is the portion of their cup. I would now gladly improve the opportunity on this occaſion to immind you of the <hi>good fight</hi> indeed, which if you fight not, you live and dye but the miſerable bond ſlaves of ſinne and ſatan, and ſo continue as miſerable as the other to all eternity: But if the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>captaine</hi> of our <hi>ſalvation,</hi> enable you to fight this fight (as this deceaſed ſervant of the Lord hath done) and if in him you be more then conquerours, then when death
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:158543:4"/> ſeizeth upon you, you will lay hold on eternall life as your Crowne; and as ſure as the Lord lives, the eternall joyes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven will be the portion of your cup.</p>
            <p>But to omit farther circumlocation, take notice that this Text containeth <hi>Paul</hi>'s charge to <hi>Timothy, to fight the good fight of faith and to lay hold on eternall life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But what's that to us (may ſome ſay) <hi>Timothy</hi> was a Miniſter, and the charge is given to him to behave himſelfe as a valiant Souldier in his miniſteriall calling, againſt all oppoſitions which he was likely to meet with.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Sometimes the Apoſtle ſpeaks to him as a Miniſter, ſometimes as a profeſſor and private Chriſtian; intimating unto us hereby, that this charge belongs both to Miniſters and people.</p>
            <p>All Chriſtians, both Paſters and people, are Souldiers, often expoſed to great ſtreights and difficulties; yet the ſpirit of God in this chapter directs them to help themſelves three wayes;</p>
            <list>
               <label>by</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 Flight.</item>
                     <item>2 Purſuit.</item>
                     <item>3 Fight.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, by Flight: There are four particulars in the preceding verſes which Chriſtians muſt flye from as from Serpents and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils elſe they are likely to be overcome.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Not conſenting to wholſome words, even the words of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and to the doctrine which is according unto godlineſſe, <hi>ver.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Proud doting about queſtions and ſtriſes of words.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The evill effects and conſequences of theſe, which are five:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Envy.</item>
               <item>2 Strife.</item>
               <item>3 Raylings.</item>
               <item>4 Evill ſurmizings.</item>
               <item>5 Perverſe diſputings of men of corrupt minds, <hi>ver.</hi> 4 5. And a motive hereunto in <hi>verſe</hi> 7, 8.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="4">4 Curſed covetouſneſſe, manifeſted by an inordinate deſire to be rich; the love of money being the root of all evill, which makes men fall into many fooliſh and hurtfull luſts, which pierceth them through with many ſorrowes; nay, which drowne them in deſtruction and perdition. Oh man of God
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:158543:4"/> (whether Miniſters or private Chriſtian) help thy ſelfe, ſecure thy ſoule, by flying from theſe, <hi>verſe</hi> 9, 10. and part of the 11.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by Purſuit of ſix friends (expreſt in the 11. ver.) which if we gain not on our ſide, there is little hope for our ſouls to eſcape a cruell overthrow and eternall raine: therefore O man of God <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> follow after (or eagerly purſue) theſe (as hounds do the Hare) which are 1 Rightcouſneſſe. 2 Godlineſſe. 3 Faith. 4 Love. 5 Patience. 6 Meekneſſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, by Fight; in the words of the Text: in which you</p>
            <list>
               <label>have two things.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 An Injunction: <hi>Timothy</hi> muſt fight the good fight of faith.</item>
                     <item>2 A provocation hereunto: Then <hi>Timothy</hi> may be aſſured that he ſhall be crowned with eternall life. I ſhall onely pitch up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Injunction, and bring in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation in the Application.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In the Injunction you have three things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The fight that muſt be ſought, <hi>viz.</hi> The fight of faith.</item>
               <item>2 The deſcription of this fight: It is a good fight.</item>
               <item>3 The combatants or ſouldiers that muſt fight it, <hi>viz.</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and all other chriſtians; from whence there ariſe three points of doctrine to be proſecuted.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>Doctr.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 That there is a fight in faith.</item>
                     <item>2 This fight is a good fight.</item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Timothy</hi> and all of his ſpirit muſt fight it. To begin with the firſt.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, there is a fight in faith, it is a combating and conflicting grace: I doe not ſay that no other grace is militant but this, but what grace ſoever hath fleſh and blood, and devill, ſtrong luſts, and corruptions to fight againſt, this hath much more. There is indeed a fight in humility, combating againſt horrid pride and curſed vaine-glory; there is a fight in love, combating againſt malice, envy and hatred (thoſe cruell enemies to the ſoule) a fight in patience againſt murmuring, repining impatient diſcontentedneſſe; a fight in chaſtity againſt ſcorching and broyling luſts; in liberality againſt covetonſneſſe; in tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance againſt drunkenneſſe: but faith is the Captaine grace, and the maine in a chriſtian combate againſt theſe and many ſuch ſpirituall enemies.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:158543:5"/>
            <p> None that know any thing in Chriſtianity, but knowes this, that there is a fig it in faith, no ſooner is a man a beleever but he is a warriour: But for the proſecution of this point, I ſhall ſhew you three things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The paralell between corporall and ſpirituall warre.</item>
               <item>2 The maine particulats wherein faith is engaged in this combate.</item>
               <item>3 By what ſtrength this fight is managed.</item>
            </list>
            <p>To ſhew you wherein the reſemblance holds in every thing would be too tedious: the paralell holds chiefly in theſe five par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Souldiers are gathered together, and battels brought on by the ſound of a Trumpet, ſo are true beleevers and worſhippers in the Lord's mountaine to be brought on to his ſpirituall warfare by the ſound of the Lord's Trumpet, <hi>viz.</hi> the powerfull preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpell, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27. 2. which as a ſhrill ſound of a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet ſummons them hereunto.</p>
            <p>The ſervice of the Tabernacle (which muſt be managed by faith in the Meſſiah, or elſe abominable) is twice ſaid in th'origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall to be the warfare of the Tabernacle, and this is brought on by the ſound of the Trumpet, <hi>Numb.</hi> 8. 24. 25.</p>
            <p>Againe, 1 <hi>Cor. 14. 8. for if the Trumpet give an uncertaine ſound, who ſhall prepare to the battell?</hi> and what is this Trumpet but the plaine preaching of the Word in ſuch a manner as it may be eaſily underſtood elſe none will be excited to this war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare: for as the ſound of the Trumpet, ſo the Word ſerves not onely to teach what is to be done, but to excite with courage to <note place="margin">Pareus in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oc.</note> performe the duty.</p>
            <p n="2">II. In fighting there are encounterers and ſtrong oppoſites; ſo in this fight of faith it meets with ſtrong oppoſites, world, fleſh and devill, and all that they can muſter up and bandy together: Faith is like <hi>Thmael</hi> in this caſe; the hands of all theſe are againſt faith, and the hand of faith is againſt them all.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Satan hates faith and all the faithfull, and would not leave any alive in the world; as the King of <hi>Syria</hi> ſaid to his 32 Capraines concerning the King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo ſaith ſatan con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <note place="margin">1 King. 22. 31</note> faith and the faithfull; fight neither againſt ſmall nor great but againſt theſe onely.</item>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:158543:5"/>
               <item> 2 The world is a deadly enemy: witneſſe
<list>
                     <item>1 In preaching of it; the world hates it.</item>
                     <item>2 In profeſſing of it; the world ſcornes it.</item>
                     <item>3 In practizing of it; what a world of malice is conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually manifeſted againſt it?</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>3 The fleſh and carnail reaſon cry it downe, as the moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd thing in the world.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="3">III. In fighting there is much difficulty ſo in beleeving; the hardeſt thing in the world to beleeve; It's <hi>durum certamen,</hi> a hard combat; a wraſtling with principalities and powers, which <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 12.</note> are not overcome but with much difficulty; as when a poore Chriſtian gotten from under the ſlavery of a Turke, or a Prore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from the cruelty of a barbarous Cavaleir, he is purſued by his potent and cruell enemy, who againe layes hold on him, to reduce him to his former thraldome. Imagine with what vigor he wraſtles with his enemy, and with what difficulty he eſcapes his fury. Or as a poore man throwne over-board; and ready to ſink under water, his friend reacheth him out a pole, at which he catcheth, and no ſooner got hold on't, but his enemy ſtrives (by rapping, knocking and cutting his fingers) to make him let goe his hold; yet he cryes and holds and holds and cryes, but with much difficulty: So it is often with a poore beleever, got from under the tyranoy of Satan: His arch enemy would faine reduce him to his former condition and by temptation layes hold on him yet the poore beleeving ſoule eſcapes through much diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty: Chriſt tenders and offers himſelfe to him, to free him from that gulfe of wofull miſery whereinto he is ſo deeply plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; with difficulty faith layes hold on this Object; no ſooner doth it ſo, but Saran is ready to beat him off from his hold; yet faith (like a brave ſpirited child) fights and cryes, and cryes and fights weeps and prayes and prayes and weeps, and ſtill keeps his hold.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. In fighting there is a Victory aimed at, and whoſoever goeth a warfare, hath an eye and aime at this; ſo there is in the fight of faith an eye and aime at victory: It's this which makes the beleever triumph in the midſt of miſery; when wealth is gone, faith tels him of a treaſure in Heaven; when husband, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or friend is gone, faith tels us of a better husband, and better
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:158543:6"/> father and friends in Heaven, when life comes to a period faith tels of an eternall life of glory, of which he can never be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaved.</p>
            <p n="5">V. There is violence uſed in other fights to get the victory, ſo there is in the fight of faith. Mat. 11. 12. <hi>The Kingdome of Heaven ſuffereth violence, and the violent take it by ſorce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> 2. What are the main particulars wherein faith is enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, or the buſineſſe of faith, in which (if it be at all) it cannot but combat, fight, and contend?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In twelve particulars faith is engaged, as a combating and conflicting grace, at which I muſt but hint without illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to maintaine all divine revelations; to ſet to the ſeale that God is true, that he muſt have the honour of all divine truths revealed in his holy word, though they ſeeme to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <note place="margin">Rom. 4. 17.</note> but Myſteries, Riddles and Paradoxes; and in beleeving theſe, and cloſing with them to become a foole that he may be wiſe, 1 Cor. 3. 18. As for example:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 To beleeve the doctrine of the glorious Trinity in Unity, that three ſhould be one, and one three, that the Sonne ſhould be as old as his Father, and the holy Ghoſt proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from them both, equall with them both.</item>
               <item>2 The doctrine of the creation: that God made all things of nothing, which worldly reaſon contradicts, ſaying, <hi>ex nihilo, nihil fit:</hi> out of nothing, nothing can be made: and ſo we might runne over all till we come to the doctrine of reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and laſt judgement.</item>
               <item>3 To beleeve that bodies ſo long dead ſhall riſe againe; nay, bodies buried in the ſea, and devoured by fiſhes, and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall fiſhes ſwallowing ſeverall parts, and though cut into a thouſand pieces and given to the fowles of the ayre, yet to beleeve that theſe bodies ſhall riſe againe.</item>
               <item>4 To beleeve that ſoule and body, ſo long ſeparated ſhall at the laſt day be re-united to receive either the fulneſſe of bleſſedneſſe, or the fulneſſe of curſedneſſe: theſe and many ſuch ſeem to be doctrines full of abſurdity, and therefore cannot be beleeved without a combat.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Secondly, to keep the ſoule from ſinking into deſperation at
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:158543:6"/> the ſight of ſinne and ſinfulneſſe, when ſinne in the nature, acts, aggravations and effects are cleerly diſcovered, and ſet home to the conſcience; it's then in the nature of every heart to play the part of <hi>Judas,</hi> and the deſperate Jaylor, to lay violent hands on themſelves and with the poore fiſh to leap out of the frying-pan into the fire; now the buſineſſe of faith is to hold a man up by the coin that he ſink not in theſe waters, and ſo be irrecoverably drowned in deſparation: but all this is not done without a combat.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to bring a man from ſelf-ſufficiency and ſelf depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, to reſt upon Chriſt alone: Herein there is a two-fold ſelfe that faith fighteth with and overcommeth.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Selfe-oppoſition to Chriſt.</item>
               <item>2 Selfe-mixture with Chriſt.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1 The firſt tendereth a ſufficiency of her own to the ſoul with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt; hence cloſeth not with Chriſt, but reſts on ſelfe and its owne doings.</p>
            <p>2 The ſecond ſeems to abhorre ſuch prophaneneſſe as to <q>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend <note place="margin">Phil. 3 verſe. 4, &amp;c.</note> on ſelfe without Chriſt for life and for ſalvation; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore placeth onely ſufficiency in Chriſt alone to make the ſoul bleſſed, but in point of applying and receiving this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe to it ſelfe, mixeth her own parts, duties or ſomething of ſelfe with Chriſt; and ſo ſerveth her ſelfe and her owne wayes in the ſufficiency of Chriſt:</q> But the Lord enables a beleever by faith to come from ſelfe in both theſe particulars, and reſt wholly on Chriſt alone, but not without a combate and conflict: Nay, the buſineſſe of faith is to bring a man from ſelfe in other particulars; as (contrary to that in <hi>Job)</hi> to <note place="margin">Job 36. 21. Heb. 11. 25. Acts 7. 60.</note> chooſe the greateſt affliction rather then the leaſt ſinne: 2. To recompence the greateſt evill with the greateſt good: 3. To rely on a word without ſenſe rather then to reſt on ſenſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a word: 4. To take as much paines in the duties of piety for Heaven, as if there were no Chriſt to bring him thither; and when he hath done all to account himſelfe an unprofitable ſervant and ſo attribute all to Chriſt, as if he had not been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with any parts, nor performed any duties at all &amp;c. but <note place="margin">Phil. 4. 13.</note> all this is not without a combate.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:158543:7"/>
            <p> Fourthly, to bring Chriſt and the ſoule together, and to give them poſſeſſion of each other, whereby Chriſt comes to dwell in the heart, and the ſoule in Chriſt; this cannot be without a <note place="margin">Eph 3. 17.</note> combate, becauſe ſatan puts ſorth all his power and policy to hinder this.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, to purifie the heart and to make riddance of a mans <note place="margin">Acts 15. 9.</note> prevailing corruptions, ſo as (though they remain) yet they reigne not in the ſoule: But this cannot be without a combat, becauſe ſinne and luſt are ſuch enemies as have no ingenuity nor good manners and therefore will not be gotten out by faire meanes, by entreaties and the like. <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 29, 30. Rom 4. 18, 19, 20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, to give the ſoule poſſeſſion of the promiſes, and to enable it to reſt on them; which is not done without a combat.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, to make the ſoule facile and tractable to God's mind, and pliable to yeeld obedience to all God's Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; it's faith that makes a man ſee that it is God that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> to run the wayes of his Commandements; it's faith againe that is as the oyle to the wheels, to enable a man with alacrity to run: But oh the combat of fleſh againſt faith herein, what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever feels it not?</p>
            <p>Eighthly, to unglevv, unſcrew and looſen a man from the world, by preſenting better objects unto him: this is done by faith, but not without a combat. <note place="margin">Heb. 11 24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Ninthly, to bring a mans neck under the croſſe and to enable him to beare the greateſt indignities, loſſes, croſſes, with invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible patience; ſee what faith enabled the Patriarchs to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 36, 37. but this is not done without a combat: fleſh and blood puts in here againe, like <hi>Peter</hi> to Chriſt, Pitty thy ſelfe Maſter, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, To give a man a holy reſt in God, a holy peace com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and confidence in God; the one maine and principall reſt that Saints aime at is God in Chriſt, and this makes any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar reſts truly repoſes to them indeed: Now faith engageth it ſelfe to bring the ſoule to ſuch a reſt in God through Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 11. this cannot bewithout a combat, to bring a man into ſuch a condition, as to make every day a feaſt day, a day of reſt, ſweetly repoſing himſelfe in the boſome of God in Chriſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:158543:7"/> with confidence: Oh there are many enemies, labour to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt <note place="margin">☞</note> this ſweet reſt, with whom faith combats, both to bring the ſoule to and to keep it as by a garriſon in this reſt, till it arive at eternall reſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 6, 7. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Eleventhly, to make a man willing to dye, by preſenting hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe to come, and the vanity and ſinfulneſſe of this life; yet <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 23.</note> this is not done without a combate; as we ſee by the example of the Saints: Beleevers only are willing to dye, and faith makes them ſo, after the combate with, and conqueſt over thoſe ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to this ſweet frame of willingneſſe, to be diſſolved and to be with Chriſt, which is beſt of all.</p>
            <p>Twelfthly, to make Chriſtians ſay in all theſe, we are more then Conquerours (that is) moſt glorious and eminent Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 37. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 John 5. 4.</note> and this by faith: There can be no ſuch conqueſt without faith, and you never heard of a conqueſt without a combate. Thus you ſee there is a fight in beleeving, a reall, yet ſpirituall fight, cloſely and inwardly managed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> 3. How, or by what ſtrength is this fight of faith ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer in generall; not by any ſtrength of its own, as it is a grace, but in way and ſtrength of dependency upon God and his grace; though faith be the chiefe rooting, Captaine Grace; and all other graces are (as it were) to bind the towell about them, and waſh the feet of this grace, yet take faith from dependancy, and it will be as another grace; as <hi>Sampſon</hi> ſaid of his haire, <hi>cut off this and I ſhall be like another man:</hi> It's not any power of faith that gets the victory, but the ſword of the Lord and <hi>Gideon,</hi> it's the power of the Lord joyning with his owne work of faith in the heart, that gets the victory. Thus much of the Doctrinall part of this point: the Application will be coin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident with the Application of the two doctrines remaining, which for brevity ſake ſhall be united into one; which being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded, application ſhall be made of them altogether: the poynt is this, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That it's the duty of all Paſtors and people to fight the good <note place="margin">Doctr. 2 and 3 united.</note> fight of faith. For the explication and confirmation hereof, conſider.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:158543:8"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Qu.</hi> 1. That this fight of faith is two-ſold,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Internall.</item>
               <item>2 Externall.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>1 Internall, when a beleever fights againſt his luſts and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and ſatans wiles; as appeares by theſe Scriptures, 2 <hi>Cor. 10. 3. Eph. 6. 11. 1 Pet.</hi> 2. 11.</item>
               <item>2 Externall, when a man couragiouſly ſtands up in the Cauſe of Chriſt and ſuffers afflictions and perſecutions for Chriſt, and is not overcome by them; as theſe Scriptures demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, 2 <hi>Cor. 15. 31, 32. 2 Cor.</hi> 11. 23, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Tim. 1. 18. 19. 20. 2 Tim.</hi> 2. 3, 4.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> 2. Why this fight, is it called a good fight?</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1 Becauſe a good God is the Author of it; we need not feare, it's a good fight, when God appoints the field.</item>
               <item>2 In regard of the Generall, or Leader of this Army, which is Chriſt: He never ſinned, yet in ſome reſpect it may be ſaid, that he fought the good fight of faith; therefore it muſt needs be good. <note place="margin">Revel. 17. 14.</note>
               </item>
               <item>3 The good Spirit of God is the guide and conductor in this combat; therefore it muſt needs be good.</item>
               <item>4 The weapons with which we muſt fight, are appointed and prepared by God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. Therefore a good fight.</item>
               <item>5 Becauſe it is for a good Cauſe, and it appeares to be a good Cauſe:
<list>
                     <item>1 Becauſe it is to preſerve God's glory againſt all oppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of it, and ſuch perſons and things as would eclipſe and darken it.</item>
                     <item>2 Beauſe it is for truth and righteouſneſſe ſake, <hi>Jud.</hi> 3. As one ſaid, it muſt needs be a good Religion that ſuch a wretch as <hi>Nero</hi> perſecuted; ſo that muſt needs be a good fight that oppoſeth and weakneth the power of ſuch enemies as Devil World and Fleſh.</item>
                     <item>3 Becauſe it is to preſerve a precious ſoule, better worth then the whole world, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 26.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>6 In regard it hath a good iſſue and event. <hi>viz.</hi> eternall life: though a beleever meet with many a knock and much hardſhip and difficulties i'th' combate, yet he ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be crowned with victory: In all theſe reſpects it's ſaid to be a good fight.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:158543:8"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Qu.</hi> 3 But why muſt all of <hi>Timothie's</hi> ſpirit fight this fight of faith, which ſo cleerly appeares to be a good fight?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Becauſe God will have all the ſeed of the woman tried; all ſuch muſt look to have their heel bruiſed by the old <note place="margin">Gen. 3d 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Serpent; therefore all muſt warre.</p>
            <p>2 Becauſe Satan beares a like hatred againſt all; he ſeeks whom he may devour, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 8. as the Wolfe will ſpare none in the flock neither Ram nor Sheep nor Lamb that he can come by; ſo Satan-world and fleſh will neither ſpare Miniſter nor Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, nor common ſort of people: therefore all beleevers of what rank and quality ſoever, muſt (in oppoſition to this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon foe) fight the good fight of faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> 4. Why doth the Lord ſuffer this ſpirituall warfare, whereby the ſoules of beleevers are ſo annoyed with ſuch ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies? could not the Lord have brought beleevers ſoules to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life without this?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though God at the firſt work of faith in the ſoule could have utterly aboliſhed all ſuch ſpirituall adverſaries, yet he lets them remaine even after effectuall calling, while we are here militant in this world; for theſe reſpects:</p>
            <p n="1">1 To ſhew his power that he can keep beleevers, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the continuall danger they are in: God can carry one of his ſouldiers quite through all the quarters and armies of the black Prince of darkneſſe without any hurt; he can make his Sheep feed fat in the midſt of Wolves, and his Lillies grow and flouriſh in the midſt of Thornes, and beleevers upright in the middeſt of ſtrong enemies, till they become triumphant in glory.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Hereby the graces of God's Spirit are raiſed and exerciſed to the glory of God who wrought them, which (if they met with no oppoſition) would not ſo gloriouſly appeare; as in the time of peace many choyce ſpirits lye undiſcovered, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3 It is equall we ſhould warre before we triumph, that we fight this good fight on earth before we reigne in heavenly glory.</p>
            <p n="4">4 It makes grace here and glory hereafter more ſweet and precious; hence the Lord often brings a ſoule to Heaven by the gates of hell, and to a triumphant condition in glory, by a mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:158543:9"/> condition on earth, which is ſweetned by this meanes; for how pleaſant is peace after warre you may imagine?</p>
            <p>The firſt Uſe of what truths have been explicated and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Uſe</hi> 1.</note> unto you, is of tryall, whether you be Souldiers of Chriſt in a militant way againſt Chriſt's and your ſoule's ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all enemies or whether yet you be vaſſals of the devill. Here are no newters: <hi>He that is not with me is againſt me</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <note place="margin">Matth. 12. 30.</note> you are certainly every one of you militant either under Chriſt's or Satan's banner: Now the ſame queſtion in the miniſtry of the Word is propounded by Chriſt, which was once by <hi>Jehu, Who is on my ſide, who?</hi> 2 King. 9. 32. If you be on Chriſt's ſide, then are you beleevers in a militant way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> How ſhall we know whether we be ſo or not?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. If you be gathered and brought on by the ſound of the Trumpet, <hi>viz.</hi> the powerfull preaching of the Word, the ordinary way which the Lord takes to prepare a people for this ſpirituall battell, by enlightning their eyes to ſee their danger, to ſee their enemies of whom they are in danger, the multitude, <note place="margin">Iſa. 27. 13. 1 Cor. 14. 8. Heb. 10. 32.</note> ſubtilty and ſtrength of theſe adverſaries, and the ſoules weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in it ſelfe to vanquiſh them; but with all its ſtrength; by faith in her Captaine the Lord Jeſus, when once ſavingly wrought on: Then here are according to the paralell before, five ſorts to be ſet by, who may have the name and profeſſion of a Souldier, for the credit on't, or for ſome baſe ſiniſter reſpect, or other, yet utter ſtrangers to this ſpirituall warfare: As many amongſt us have the name of a ſouldier and martiall men flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it in their Buffe and great Scarfes; but yet others, and their owne conſciences know they are no Souldiers, and have neither will nor skill to fight, but baſely thruſt themſelves into that noble and honourable profeſſion of a ſouldier for ſome ſordid and ſiniſter reſpect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> But who are theſe?</p>
            <p n="1">1 All ſuch as hate the ſound of the Drum and Trumpet have no diſpoſition of a ſouldier; ſo all theſe haters of the Lords Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet. the ſhrill cleare and ſharp preaching of the Goſpell by ſuch and ſuch Miniſters (who dare not let it give an uncertaine ſound) are yet none of theſe that are fighting the good fight of faith.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Such as are not ſenſible of any enemies to their ſoules
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:158543:9"/> ſpirituall good here, and eternall good hereafter.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Such as aime at no victory, or think to attaine it without a fight.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That fight, but uſe no violence; all newters and lukewarme perſons are here excluded.</p>
            <p n="5">5 But chiefly theſe that pleaſe themſelves with a ſtrong conceit that they are as good ſouldiers as the beſt, and doubt not but they are fighting the good fight of faith, and ſhall certainly lay hold on eternall life; yet think their multitude of ſtrong and ſubtill enemies are eaſily overcome; they think it's an eaſie matter to beleeve, and to be a Chriſtian ſouldier indeed, and ſo find no difficulty in this fight, which is a cleere demonſtration that they never were in combate and conflict, and ſo are no ſouldiers of Jeſus Chriſt: others indeed, like ſome ſouldiers in ſhew and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall profeſſion, are in ſome light skirmiſhes of which they will exceedingly bragge, and make this an argument, that they are approved ſouldiers; ſo many will conclude themſelves to be undoubtedly ſouldiers of the Lord Jeſus, becauſe they have been now and then exerciſed with ſome combats and conflicts, and theſe they will often talk of and boaſt of, and from hence gather arguments of their ſpirituall good ſouldery, and fighting the good fight, when there is no ſuch matter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But what then is the difference?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The difference lyes in</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>three things:</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 The manner</item>
                           <item>2 The aime and end</item>
                           <item>3 The event or ſucceſſe</item>
                        </list>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>of the Fight.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Sometimes there appeares a meer deluſion; when two luſts are together by the eares, as Covetouſneſſe and Prodigality are ſtriving which ſhall prevaile, in the meane time the poore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull ſouldier thinks he is combating againſt an enemy: But admit a combate, yet there is much difference between the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batings of regenerate and unregenerate.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the manner, in four particulars. 1. A naturall man though he fight againſt ſpirituall enemies, yet it is coldly and liſtleſly: Like <hi>Ephraim,</hi> turnes his back in the day of battell, <note place="margin">Pſal. 77. 9.</note> and having got advantages, will not follow them, <hi>(Eg.) Saul</hi> had ſome fits of ſorrow for ſinne, and ſome purpoſes to leave it; but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:158543:10"/> how cold was this? as appeares by his preſent hot purſuit of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Sam 26. 20, 21, 22.</note> againe. Light ſometimes ſhines in dark ſt priſons and hard Marbles ſometimes ſtand a drops, and rocky hearts ſometimes relent; but contrary, where the Spirit of God is in the heart of a beleever, it makes him a man of power and might powerfully and mightily to reſiſt ſinne, to follow his advantages and purſue <note place="margin">Col. 1. laſt.</note> his victories, and ſtill to fight with a kill or be kild; whereas the cold fighting againſt an enemy, and flow purſuit of him when they have him at an advantage is a cleer diſcovery of ſuch to have onely the name and profeſſion of ſouldiers.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A naturall man fighteth againſt ſome of the enemies of his Lord and of his poore ſoule, but not againſt them all; he onely ſtrives againſt ſome groſſe ſinnes, ſuch as the world cryes ſhame of, the lawes of the land take hold of, or ſuch as are too coſtly to maintaine, or ſuch as fill the conſcience with horrour; it's contrary with a gracious heart like <hi>David,</hi> hateth every falſe <note place="margin">Pſal. 119 128. Pſal. 18. 33.</note> way, and ſtrives againſt his peculiar ſinne, the ſinne of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion or conſtitution, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A naturall man in his ſtriving and fighting againſt ſome ſinnes only, doth but lop the branches; a true ſpirituall ſouldier of Chriſt ſtriketh at the very root of corruption, and is not quiet till <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 24. 2 Pet. 1. 4.</note> he find his ſinfull diſpoſition changed, and himſelfe made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the divine nature.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The one fights and ſtrives hard againſt ſinne by fits and ſtarts, when he is Sermon-ſick, or after ſome heavy loſſe or croſſe, then he is perſwaded ſinne is the cauſe of all this miſery, and now he begins to ſtrive againſt it, and pray for power and ſtrength againſt it; but the other holds on conſtantly fighting the good fight, and gives not over till he hath finiſhed his <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 7.</note> courſe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond difference lyes in both their aimes and which <note place="margin">II. <hi>In the end.</hi>
               </note> they have in this their combating and conflicting with ſinne, which appeares in three reſpects:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The regenerate, or the true Chriſtian ſouldier fights againſt ſinne as Gods enemy; hence he gets up to help the Lord againſt the mighty, that Gods enemies may be weakned, that God may have the ſole dominion, that his lawes may be kept unviolated, that his promiſes and threars may be beleeved, &amp;c. Contrary, a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:158543:10"/> meere naturall man hath ſome ſtrife againſt ſinne, not as ſinne, but in regard of ſome ill conſequences of it; as to prevent ſhame, horrour here, and hell hereafter: he loves the forbidden fruit (as the dog his hot broth) but dares not meddle with it for feare of ſcalding his lips: But the true ſouldier of Chriſt corflicts by vertue of that antipathy which is betweene his renewed na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and ſinne: As it is with a man (by reaſon of the antipathy between him and a Serpent) he cannot think of a Serpent, but his ſpirit riſeth againſt it but much more when this Serpent comes neere him, moſt of all, when invironed with a multitude of them, ready to leap upon him and ſting him; ſo it is with a beleever; he cannot think of ſinne as ſinne againſt God, but his ſpirits riſe with indignation of it, much more when it neerly approaches to his ſoule; but when he is beſet with ſinne, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered to be ſtung and poyſoned with it, and ſo Gods Name diſhonoured, then all that is within him is muſtered up againſt it, and if he had a thouſand times more ſpirit and ſtrength, all ſhould be imployed againſt it in this combate, as it is Gods ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, as well as the enemy of his owne ſoule.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A naturall mans end in ſtriving againſt ſinne is, that he may have ſome temporall advantages thereby; as eaſe, and peace, and wealth, and credit, and friends; the contrary, if he have any aime at all at gaine, it is to his ſoule here and glory hereafter, which he knows cannot be had without a victorious fighting the good fight of faith.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The naturall man combats onely to ſubdue ſinne (which is well) but if this be all, he is but like <hi>Ephraim,</hi> half-baked; if onely ſinnes be ſubdued, he will be diſ-appointed of his aime and end herein too; for if he have no other aime, his ſinnes will never be conquered.</p>
            <p>The ſpirituall man hath a further aime and end in his combate then onely to ſubdue ſinne, <hi>viz.</hi> to get corruption ſubdued, that Chriſt may reigne, that ſinne may be puld up, that Chriſt may be planted i'th roome; he takes revenge on diſobedience, that he may be more obedient; he puts off rioting and drunkenneſſe, chambering and wantonneſſe, ſtrife and envying, that he may <note place="margin">Rom. 13, 13, 14.</note> further put on the Lord Jeſus, and walk honeſtly as in the day; he forbeares the ſuperſtitious obſervation of dayes; that he may
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:158543:11"/> obſerve the Lords day the better; he forbeares to prophane the Lords day, that he may ſanctifie it aright: But it's contrary with the naturall man in his ſtrife and fighting; if he can ſuppreſſe ſinne he thinks it enough; he hath none of theſe aimes and ends in his fight, he never labours for a part in Chriſt, and his grace and growth therein.</p>
            <p>The third difference is in the iſſue and ſucceſſe. A natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <note place="margin">III. <hi>In the ſucceſſe.</hi>
               </note> man fights and ſtrives againſt corruptions, but is uſually foyled and overcome; the ſpirituall man gets the victory; and if he be foyled at any time, he gathers ſtrength hereby, and ſets upon his ſpirituall enemies with greater violence and better ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Uſe is of Information. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Uſe</hi> 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That it's not ſo eaſie a matter to be a Chriſtian; is't an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie matter to fight couragiouſly, skilfully, watchfully &amp; conſtantly with a multitude of ſtrong, ſubtill enemies, and vanquiſh them? Is't an eaſie matter to chop off the right hand and pull out the right eye? No, no: The Chriſtians that lead ſuch eaſie and pleaſant lives, and never find any ſuch combating, are but Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in profeſſion onely; though this fight be not managed by any ſtrength of a mans owne, but the Lord Jeſus himſelfe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables the ſoule by faith to, runne and winne; yet it is not without difficulty, and to fight and be victorious, yet with dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it is not ſafe to conclude of the happy condition of all that dye quietly, nor of the bad condition of thoſe that dye in conflict. &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thoſe that enter into the profeſſion of Chriſtianity, into this ſpirituall warfare, and never reckon aforehand what it will <note place="margin">Luk: 14, 31.</note> coſt them are never likely to hold out, but have a brand of folly upon them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This alſo diſcovers the folly of ſuch as think to get the Crowne without a fight, or begin to fight when good ſouldiers finiſh it; namely in their old age, when the time of their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture drawes nigh; when <hi>Paul</hi> finiſheth his courſe, many think it's <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4, 6, 7,</note> then time enough to begin theirs: this is all one as if one ſhould ſay, I will fight under the banner of the utter enemy of my Prince, till my old, lame, decreped age, and then I will offer my
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:158543:11"/> ſervice to him, which (ſaith the Prophet) is a curſed and a deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <note place="margin">Mal. 3, 8.</note> thing: this is all one, as if one ſhould let his enemy get him downe and weaken him, and then think it's time enough to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; as <hi>England</hi> deales with their corporall ſo many now adayes deale with their ſpirituall adverſaries: Doe they not let their enemies encreaſe, <hi>Iriſh Rebels</hi> invade the Land, poſſeſſe Forts, Caſtles, Countries, and have the better end of the ſtaffe, then think it's time enough to ariſe as one man, and make oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition? ſo fooliſh are moſt of us in our ſpirituall fight, we let luſt take poſſeſſion of the heart, and fortifie, and make it ſelfe very ſtrong, and then we are ready to think it's time enough to ſet upon this duty of fighting <hi>the good fight of faith:</hi> the ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſideration of this Scripture, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 7. may prevent this <note place="margin">Revel. 2. 7.</note> folly; the Spirit of God in this place holds out</p>
            <list>
               <label>three things unto us:</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>There is no communion with Chriſt where there is no oppoſition againſt corruption.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Where there is no fighting there is no conqueſt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>And where there is no overcomming there is no eating of the Tree of Life,</hi> (that is) <hi>no ſalvation.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The holy Ghoſt doth not ſay, he that fights a little (for credit, honour, or ſuch ſiniſter reſpects, and then gives over and runnes out of the Field and layes downe his Commiſſion, and will fight no more) ſhall eat of the tree of life, but he that ſo fights and overcomes <hi>ſhall eat of the Tree of life that is in the midſt of the Garden.</hi> Oh then be aſhamed of ſuch thoughts to attaine Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <note place="margin">Non eſt eter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is mollis ad aſtra via.</note> with ſo much eaſe; the way thither is not in a fether-bed, nor ſtrewed with ruſhes: Be aſhamed alſo of ſuch a ſordid diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, either to begin in the ſpirit, and then (baſely apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing) end in the fleſh, or to deferre the fight ſo long, till it be time to finiſh the courſe.</p>
            <p>Then be ye all in the name of Chriſt exhorted to goe on in a <note place="margin">Uſe 3. of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation.</note> military way here, that ye may be triumphant hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu. But how ſhall we fight againſt theſe ſpirituall enemies eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially our ſinfull corruptions, ſo as to overcome them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Time permits not to inſtruct and direct fully in this;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:158543:12"/> I muſt therefore ſend you to that whole armour of God, menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. 11. to 13. and doe beſeech you to ſtudy that; <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> where you are directed what ſpirituall weapons you muſt get to fight with; as alſo, how wiſely, and with what ſpiritual skill theſe ought to be uſed in this warfare; and for the preſert doe but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve theſe generall directions, imitating a good ſouldier of Jeſus Chriſt; make ſuch a one your patterne in theſe foure <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 3.</note> particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, Begin this ſpirituall warfare betime, and procraſtinate not. &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Secondly, have ſincere references as the preſervation of ſouls, the ruinating of Chriſt's and the ſoule's enemies, and in all, the advancement of Chriſt's glory.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, endure hardneſſe; uſe moderation; you know a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſleep and food ſerveth a good ſouldier, and he often lodgeth hard, and watcheth much &amp;c. Imitate him herein, and beware either of unlawfull liberties, or the inordinate uſe of lawfull which doe exceedingly hinder us in this war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, nay they doe entangle us hand and foot, and ſo unfit us for the battell; but in uſing hardſhip (as a good ſouldier) let it be with this threefold caution.
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>All this muſt be for righteouſneſſe ſake, then ye are bleſſed.</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Matth: 6. 10.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>In thy place and calling as a good ſouldier and not as a medler; you know if a ſouldier ſuffer or be ſlaint</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 15, 16</note> 
                        <hi>out of his rank, and from under his Commander, gets no honour.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>All this muſt be for thy Captaine, who will certainly recompence it: Satans ſouldiers ſuffer much, but</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 8.</note> 
                        <hi>what get they from their captaine?</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Fourthly, hold on conſtantly; all promiſes are made to this, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 7. 10.</item>
               <item>Take heed of apoſtatizing ſpirits, but ſtand to your colours, and follow the Lord Jeſus your Captaine, as well by the Croſſe as the Garden to the Crowne.</item>
            </list>
            <p>For your better encouragement herein, conſider three things: Firſt, Chriſt himſelfe is your Captaine <hi>Iſa. 63. 1. 2 Tim.</hi> 2. 3. Secondly, Chriſt your Generall is preſent, and his powerfull
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:158543:12"/> preſence may encourage you againſt all feares; a generous Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiffe dog will venture upon a Lyon in the preſence of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and what true hearted ſouldier will not fight valiantly in the eye and preſence of his Generall? and ſhall not a beleever doe as much in the preſence of Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The enemy hath received his deaths-wound by our Captaine, and now fighteth like a drone without a ſting.</p>
            <p>The laſt Uſe is a great ground of conſolation to all thoſe that <note place="margin">Uſe of conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</note> are enabled by the Lord Jeſus to fight this good fight of faith, eſpecially it's very comfortable on the death-bed: <hi>When the time of</hi> Paul's <hi>departure drew neer, what comforted him but this? 2 Tim.</hi> 4. 7. though death be called <hi>the King of feares</hi> and ſaid to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the moſt terrible of al terrible things in the world; yet ſuch as have fought this good fight of faith, may with much comfort look death in the face.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe by Chriſt the ſting of Death is taken away; death <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 55, 56, 57.</note> to ſuch is but a ſtingleſſe ſerpent, and a toothleſſe dog, which may afright but cannot hurt them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In regard of other terrours and feares when death approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth as when ſuch a bleſſed beleever is ready to ſay, <hi>farewell all my temporall good things, I ſhall never rejoyce in you more:</hi> His conſcience ſweetly anſwers, <hi>No matter, I ſhall have a better Husband and a better Father, I ſhall goe to better friends and comforts, and rejoyce in theſe to all eternity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, when he hath ſuch a thought on his death bed; <hi>What will become of my ſoul for ever?</hi> Now there are but two for evers, either for ever in weale, or for ever in woe: When a man thinks of that ſentence in <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. he looks wan; but the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this text, and the Spirit of God witneſſing to his ſpirit, that Chriſt hath enabled him to fulfill this charge, he ſweetly breaths out his laſt with theſe thoughts, <hi>I have fought the good fight of faith and ſhall be free from eternall death, and lay hold on</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>eternall life.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>May 14. 1645. Imprimatur</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOSEPH CARYL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
